Inventory of the R. Freeman Butts papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - The Foundation Disciplines and the Role of the Department, 1969-1970
  - A.E.S.A., "Social Foundations: Then and Now," Washington, D.C.., 1972 (Box 173)
  - "Reconstruction in Foundations Studies," article for publication in Education Theory, prepared by R. Freeman Butts, January, 1972
  - "Pedants, Pedagogues, and Persuaders in the Education of Teachers," by R. Freeman Butts, 1960
  - Materials used for New Orleans speech on "Charting Our Positions on the Way To...", February, 1968
  - Research Center for Education in American Liberties
  - Encyclopeadia Britannica, "Education,", 1967-1969
  - Maryland Board of Education, 1959
  - Class Materials (Box 174)
    - Education and Society, TF3000, 1961
    - Miscellaneous study materials
    - Miscellaneous class materials (Box 175)
  - A.E.S.A. (Box 176)
    - Executive Council, 1978-1980
    - Washington, D.C., November, 1978
    - Chicago, March, 1977
    - Symposium on 1st Course in Education Studies, Chicago, 1970
    - Program, Washington, D.C., 1972
    - Panel, "The Uncompleted Dream,", November, 1973
    - National Convention, "The Retreat from Schooling,", 1973
    - Annual Convention, "A Future for Foundations? Imperatives, Old and New,", 1974
    - American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, Chicago, 1975
    - National Convention, San Francisco, October 30-November 2, 1975
  - U.S. Office of Education, Citizen Education Discussion, Washington, D.C., 1975
  - Proposals for White House Conference on Education, 1974-1975
  - National Endowment for the Humanities (N.E.H.), Humanities Seminars for School Administrators, 1977
  - Telephone and communication, 1975-1976
  - University of Arizona, Seminar on Higher Education, April, 1977
  - Rockefeller Foundation Fellowship, Budget and report, 1975-1976
  - Trip to California, October-November, 1975
    - General planning (people to see)
    - Travel plans
  - General correspondence, September 1975-October 1976
  - National Society for the Study of Education, Yearbook, 1975
  - Teacher's College, Institute of Philosophy and Politics of Education
  - Cleveland Conference
    - December, 1975
    - December, 1974
    - December, 1973
  - Metropolitan School Study Council, Conference, October, 1973
  - Program for Business Administrators, University of Rochester, (cancelled), July, 1975
  - American Educational Research Association, Annual Meeting Program
    - Chicago, 1974
    - Washington, D.C., 1975
  - History of Education Society, "Future Trends in History of Education," Chicago, October, 1973 (Box 177)
  - Philosophy of Education Society, Vancouver, April, 1976
  - Futures for Corporative Education, San Antonio, Comparative and International Education Society (C.I.E.S.), 1973
  - Comparative and International Education Society.
    - Washington, D.C. conference, March, 1974
    - San Francisco conference, March, 1975
    - Toronto, February, 1976
  - Social Science Education Consortium
    - Conference at Illinois Beach Lodge, 1973
    - June, 1976
  - International Council for Educational Development
    - Higher Education for Development Project, January 1974-May 1975
    - Comparative Higher Education Meetings, 1974-1976
  - American Council on Education Annual Meeting, Washington, D.C., October, 1976
  - Texas Agricultural and Mechanical, Visiting Centennial Professor, February, 1976
  - Possible Follow-ups of Rockefeller Fellowships, Book Publishers Lectureships, University of Michigan Associates
  - Letters Announcing Receipt of Rockefeller Grant, March, 1975
  - Responses to Letters Seeking Assignment and Announcing Rockefeller Grant
  - Letters Describing Plans and Seeking Assignments, December 1979-January 1975
  - Abstracts - Public Education and Political Communities
  - Rockefeller Foundation Humanities Fellowships
    - First stage applications, due, October 15, 1974
    - Second stage applications, December, 1974
  - Second Career Suggestions
  - Ed Meade and the Ford Foundation
  - Comparative Public Education, budgets
  - Articles by R. Freeman Butts (Box 178)
    - "Something is Missing," Op Ed, May, 1983
    - Prayer in Education Week, February, 1983
    - Prayer in Wall Street Journal, March, 1983
    - Prayer Amendment in Los Angeles Times, September, 1982
    - "State Requirements of Private Schools," Education Week, October-November
    - "Church and State in American Education," two speeches, 1951, 1957
    - American Educational Studies Program, "Foundations of Education and the New Civism," speech, November, 1974
    - "Public Education in a Pluralistic Society," Midwest Philosophy of Education Society, November, 1975
    - "The Idea of Public Education in the Revolutionary Era," Fort Wayne, 1975
    - "Historical Perspectives on Civic Education in the U.S.," Task Force Working Paper, 1976
    - "Whose Twilight?" Courts Lecture Manuscript, Phi Beta Kappan, Bicentennial Issue
    - "The Case for Public Education," San Jose Festival, November, 1976
  - Vital Issues, April, 1977 (Box 179)
  - Association for Supervision and Curriculum Development
    - John Dewey Society, Houston, March, 1977
    - "A Curriculum Design for the Educated Citizen,"
      - Texts, April, 1980
      - Arrangements, Atlanta, Spring 1980
  - "The Public School as a Moral Authority," Stanford University, Convocation, May, 1977
  - "Time for a Revival of Civic Learning," PTA Today, December 1980-January 1981
  - Project 87
    - General
    - "What Society Expects from School Instruction about the Courts," Project 87 and the Bicentennial, Indiana University, October 28-31, 1980
    - "History of Teaching the Constitution," texts
  - American Bar Association, Youth Education for Citizenship, Bicentennial Leadership Conference, Houston, September, 1981
  - Phi Beta Kappa, Education Symposium at Stanford, Spring 1984
  - "Something is Missing," The Kettering Review, Winter 1984
  - David Mathews on the Role of the Kettering Foundation, 1982 (Box 180)
  - National Humanities Center, 1981-1982
  - Kettering Associates
    - Spring 1982
    - Aspen East, Wye Plantation, October 22, 1982
    - 1983-1984
    - 1984-1985
  - Lyndon B. Johnson Presidential Library Conference, March 22, 1984
  - Law in a Free Society, proposal to Kettering Foundation and correspondence, 1981
  - Domestic Policy Association and National Issues Forum
- Education of the West (teaching materials and manuscripts for book) (Box 181)
  - Topic I - Education and Culture
  - Chapter I, Primitive Cultures
  - TF 3604 - "The Education of the West"
    - Autumn, 1971
    - Autumn, 1972
    - Autumn, 1973
    - Autumn, 1974
  - Historical Theories of Social Change
  - Themes or Hypotheses to Test the Role of Education Modernization Process
  - A Conceptual Framework for the History of Education
  - Chapter I, schema and patterns
  - Theories of Civilization as Historical Process (Box 182)
  - Chapter I, Characteristics of Folk Society
  - Chapter II, Characteristics of Traditional (pre-Industrial) Civilization
  - Chapter II, Mesopotamian Civilization
  - Chapter II, The Widening Orbit of Civilization, Egypt and Mediterranean
  - Chapter III, Greek Civilization: The Wellspring of Western Education
  - Lyons, Charles H., "Scribe Culture"
  - Chapter IV, The Dispersion of Hellenistic Education
  - Chapter V, Education in the Building of Christendom (Box 183)
  - Chapter V, Education in the Formation of Western Civilization
  - Chapter VI, The 3 R's of Western Education
  - Chapter VII, Catholic and Latin Education in Europe, Asia and America
  - Chapter VII, Comparison of Aztec and Inca Education, Farrell
  - Farrell, The 16th Century Domination of Spanish America
  - Chapter VIII, Anglo-Protestant Education in Europe and North America
  - Chapter VIII, The Education Resolution in England
  - Chapter VIII, Kaestle, Karl, "A Separate Academy for the Tudor Nobility"
  - Characteristics of Modern Civilization and the Modernization Process
  - Chapter IX, The Transmutation to Modernity in the West
  - Enlightenment (Box 184)
  - R. Freeman Butts on Modernization
  - TF 6604 - Seminar in the History of Western Education
  - Ed. 6704 - Education and the Modernization Process
  - Bibliography on Modernization Process, Spring 1968
  - TF 6704 - Education and the Modernization Process in Developing Nations, (2 folders)
  - Role of Education in the Modernization Process
  - Conceptions of the Modernization Process
  - Modernity and Modern Education (Box 185)
  - Chapter X, In Pursuit of Modern Education in Europe
  - Chapter XI, Modernizing Education in the Civilization of Europe
  - 19th Century Thought
  - Chapter XIII, The American Faith in Massive Education Endeavor
  - Education in Britain, (1850-1950)
  - Education in France, (1850-1950)
  - Education in Germany, (1850-1950)
  - Education and the Modernization Process in Russia, (1700-1917)
  - Education in Russia, (1850-1950)
  - Education in Other Western European Cultures, (1850-1950) (Box 186)
  - Chapter XV, The Global Spread of Western Education
  - Chapter XVI, Education and the Civilizing Mission of the West, (1850-1950)
  - Chapter XVII, The Civilizing Mission of the West
  - Chapter XX, Late Imperialism, (1850-1950)
  - Chapter XX, Modern Education and the Onset of Modernization beyond the West in the Traditional Societies of the Late Empires
  - Imperialism and Education, (1850-1950)
  - Indian Education
  - Education in India (Box 187)
  - Onset of Modernization, Southern Asia
  - Onset of Modernization, South East Asia
  - Materials for Malaysia visit, 1969
  - Onset of Modernization, East Asia (China, Japan, Korea)
  - "The Cultural Resolution of China," Hu, C. T.
  - Oceania (New Zealand, Australia, Samoa)
  - Onset of Modernization in the Moslem world
  - Onset of Modernization, Latin America
  - Onset of Modernization, Africa (Box 188)
  - Disimperialism and the Colonial Legacy in Education, and the Reach for Modernity under National Independence
  - The Widening Gap
  - Epilogue, The Post-Modern Ecumene
  - Environmental problems
  - Task Force on Section 102 of the International Education Act: Part IV
  - East West Center, Education Seminar, materials on educational development (Box 189)
  - TF 4605 - Comparative History of Higher Education
    - Spring 1971
    - Spring 1972
  - International Council for Educational Development
  - "Pacem in Terrus III," Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions, Washington D.C., October, 1973
  - Comparative Education Society
    - General
    - "Civilization as an Historical Process"
  - Ventures in International Education
  - Orientation, foreign students, September, 1962
  - All-College Committee on International Education, Harold Taylor, 1967
  - Education Research and Development Committee, La Trobe University, Victoria, Australia, 1976
  - Trip to India and Afghanistan, 1962
  - The Education of the West (original manuscript)
  - The Education of the West (original manuscript) (Box 190)
  - The Education of the West (original manuscript) (Box 191)
- TEACHERS COLLEGE
  - "Little or No Stress on Civic Values," Cremin, Sloan, McClintock
  - Butts, R. Freeman, "Role of Teachers College in International Education"
  - Teachers College, Columbia University, Annual reports, 1961-1972
  - "Civilization Building and the Modernization Process," American Historical Association, 1966
  - Teachers College, International Education, annual reports, plans, proposals, 1969-1970 (Box 192)
  - "A Teaching College for the World," University of Indiana Publication, (2 folders)
  - Colloquium for Professor William O. Stanley, University of Illinois, 1971
  - "Reconstruction in Foundation Studies," University of Wyoming, speech, April, 1972
  - "The Mission of the Educationary in the Coming Ecumene," N.S.C.T.E., 1966
  - University of Calgary, materials for speech and seminar
  - Teachers for East Africa (T.E.A.)
    - Materials, 1964
    - Training programs at Teachers College
    - T.E.A. vs. Peace Corps
    - Teacher Education in East Africa (T.E.E.A.)
    - Peace Corps Training at Teachers College
      - First impressions of participants in Africa and later questionnaires (Box 193)
    - New Nationhood, Kabul, India
    - Association for Teacher Education in Africa (A.T.E.A.)
      - Conferences, resource materials
      - "Reconstruction in Foundations Studies," Kampala and Wyoming speeches
    - African Education from T.E.A., orientations, 1962-1963
- GENERAL
  - International education materials, 1970s
  - "International Perspectives on Civic Education," Comparative and International Education Society
  - "Education and Development in the 3rd World," Palo Alto Fellowship Forum, March, 1981 (Box 194)
  - Discussion of R. Freeman Butts' views on international education, Loyola University of Chicago
  - Materials for Cubberly Library
  - Materials for Hoover Library
  - Materials for Green Library
  - Karl Bigelow Memorial Lecture
    - Correspondence, London, 1982
    - Text, revised, 1982
    - Materials for lecture
    - Text, originals
    - Text, xeroxed copies
    - Materials for lecture (Box 195)
  - Kajubi and Thompson texts
  - British Political Literacy, (2 folders)
  - "Values and the Successor Generation," Atlantic Council
  - Research notes and clippings
    - Greece
    - Roman education (Box 196)
    - Quintilian
    - Middle Ages
    - Renaissance
    - Reformation
    - Reformation and Enlightenment, America
    - Realism and Positivism
  - Quotes on Mental Discipline
  - Ed. 202A - Intellectual Foundations of Western Education, 1954-1956
  - U.N.E.S.C.O. and the United States
  - Aspen Institute, Berlin
  - Stanford Program on International and Cross-Cultural Education (S.P.I.C.E.), Ron Herring
  - "Improving Educational Efficiency in African Countries," Education Development Center, Inc.
  - International Human Rights (Box 197)
  - Clippings - Britain, Africa and the Middle East, Tradition and Modernization
  - International clippings, 1981-1982
  - Reprints - Atlantic Council, Daedalus, National Council for the Social Studies
  - U.S. Human Rights Policy (Box 198)
  - Reprints
  - Global education, miscellaneous and international education
  - "Meaning of Global Education," Lee Anderson et al.
  - International Human Rights, National Council for the Social Studies (N.C.S.S.) Bulletin
  - Civic Literacy for Global Interdependence
  - Citizen Education for Cultural Understanding
  - Workshop on Global Education, Wingspread, Racine, Wisconsin, January, 1976
  - Civic Education Project, International Education Achievement (I.E.A.) (Box 199)
  - President's Commission on International Studies, 1978-1979
  - Miscellaneous reprints
  - "Historical Perspectives on Teacher Education," California Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, San Jose and San Diego State Universities
  - "Teacher Education and the Revival of Civic Learning," Minnesota Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, April, 1978
  - Clio Project Conference (Box 200)
    - "History and Civic Education,", August, 1984
    - Berkeley conference arrangements, August, 1984
    - Advisory council
  - California Model Curriculum Standards, 1985
  - Model Curriculum Standards, Advisory Committee
    - August-October, 1984
    - June-July, 1984
    - Materials for Advisory Committee
  - Branson, Margaret
    - "California Handbook on History,", 1982
    - "History Teaching in California,", 1983
  - California Frameworks, 1962-1981 (Box 201)
  - Framework Workshops, History and Social Studies, Stanford and Palm Springs, 1981
  - California Conference on Youth Education for Citizenship, Sacramento, March, 1983
  - California Commission on Citizenship Education
  - California Education, 1972-1984
  - The Rise Report, California, 1975
  - Educators for Social Responsibility
  - California Council for Social Studies, San Francisco, San Jose, 1981, 1984
  - National Council for Social Studies (N.C.S.S.) (Box 202)
    - Scope and Sequence Task Force, 1982-1984
      - Essentials Task Force, 1979-1980
      - Clark, Todd, letters regarding need for a National Committee on Scope and Sequence, 1979
      - "Foundations of Social Studies"
      - Miscellaneous meetings and conferences
    - Project SPAN: Social Studies/Social Science Education: Priorities, Practices and Needs, discussions at Teachers College, 1979
    - "Law in a Free Society," Addison-Wesley Publishing Co.
- American Public Education: From Revolution to Reform, 1776-1976 (manuscript) (Box 203)
  - Footnotes, author's questionnaires
  - Miscellaneous research materials
    - Handwritten copies of manuscript
      - Chapter 1
      - Chapter 2
      - Chapter 3
      - Chapter 4 - The Common School: Palladium of the Republic
      - Chapter 5 - Disjunctives
      - Chapter 7 - The Push toward Coherence, (1876-1926)
      - Chapter 8 - The Pull to Differentiation
      - Chapter 9 - The Push and Pull of Ethnicism and Racism (Box 204)
    - Typed copies of manuscript
      - Preface
      - Chapter 1
      - Chapter 2
      - Chapter 3
      - Chapter 4
      - Chapter 5 - Segmental Pluralisms: Religious and Ethnic
      - Chapter 6 - Disjunctive Pluralisms: Racial and Local
      - Chapter 7 - The Push toward Coherence: Efficiency and Discipline, (1876-1926) (Box 205)
      - Chapter 8 - The Pull of Differentiation: Individualism and Vocationalism, (1876-1926)
      - Chapter 9 - The Perils of Pluralism: Nativism and Racism, (1876-1926)
      - Chapter 10
      - Chapter 11
      - Chapter 12
    - Bibliographical notes on recommended readings, (3 folders)
    - Bibliography on American Education
  - Public Education: Revolution to Reform (Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1975) (Box 206)
    - Richard Angelo's review
    - Outlines of chapters, 1-12
    - Notes on chapters, 1-3
    - Research notes and materials
    - Chapter 1 - The Formation of the American Political Community, 1776-1800
    - Chapter 2 - The Educational Promise: Unum
    - Chapter 3 - The Educational Reality: Pluribus
    - The Child and the Curriculum
    - Background notes
    - Copies of quotations
    - Samual Hall vs. Horace Mann regarding schoolkeeping
    - Research notes and materials (Box 207)
    - Chapter 4 - The Common School: Palladium of the Republic, 1826-1876
    - Chapter 5 - Disjunctivitis: The Pathology of Plurlism, (1826-1876)
    - Negro Education in America in the 19th Century
    - Localism vs. Centralism
    - Ethnicity and (1876-1926), (1826-1876)
    - Research notes and materials
      - Chapter 7
        - The Push Toward Coherence, (1876-1926)
        - "Thorough and Efficient" Systems, (1876-1926)
        - Social Efficiency, (1876-1926)
        - Academic Standardization and Uniformity
      - Chapter 8
        - The Quest for Differentiation: Individual Development, (1876-1926)
        - The Quest for Differentiation: Vocational Competence, (1876-1926)
      - La Raza - Spanish surnames, especially Mexican Americans, Chicano
    - Handwritten copy of manuscript (Box 208)
    - Asians
    - Racial Differentiation Enforced, (1876-1926)
    - American Indians
    - Women's Education and Sex Discrimination
    - Education and the American Indian
    - Blacks
    - Research notes and materials. Chapter 9 - Ethnic Differentiation, (1876-1926) (Box 209)
    - Ethnicity around the World - Diversity
    - Busing, including Boston, 1974-1975
    - Integration, Busing, Local Control, (1973-1974)
    - "What Difference Do Schools Make?"
    - "Ineqality of Financial Support - Public Attitudes Toward Public Schools"
    - Poor, Disadvantaged, Urban Unrest, clippings
    - Youth Dissent in the, 1960s and 1970s (Box 210)
    - Public and Private Schools
    - The Ford Administration, 1974-1975
    - Liberalism and the Role of Government, clippings
    - The Political Climate, 1973-1974
    - The Profession: Reform from the Progressive Era, 1970-1973
    - Education and the Intellectual Life
    - The Public and the Private
    - State's Rights in Education: Local, State, Federal (Box 211)
    - Nixon Impeachment and the Watergate Trials, 1974
    - The Watergate Tapes, 1974
- EXPERIMENTAL COLLEGE (Box 212)
  - Summer Seminar, early plans, 1983
  - Convocation, 1982; (2 folders)
  - Autobiography, presentation to Northern California group, October, 1979
  - Reviews, Publications and Historical Moments
  - Association for American Colleges (A.A.C.) Commendation for Experimental College
  - Cynthia Brown on Meiklejohn
  - Marge Frantz, Santa Cruz
  - R. F. Butts on Experimental College (Box 213)
  - Reunion, Annapolis, 1957
  - Meiklejohn's views (Hutchins and Dewey)
  - In Praise of Meiklejohn
  - Wisconsin I.L.S.
  - San Jose and Berkeley
  - The Moral Philosophy Course and Meiklejohn
  - Seven Locks Press
  - Notes on Powell and Cynthia Brown
  - Research project proposals (N.I.E. and Carnegie)
  - Alexander Meiklejohn Group, 1974-1978 (Box 214)
  - University of Wisconsin, Green Bay
  - Reunion-50th Anniversary, September, 1977
  - Bass, Jossey, "Classics in Liberal Education"
  - Materials, 1932-1938
  - Miscellany
- GENERAL
  - Journal of Teacher Education (J.T.E.) (Box 215)
    - Special issue, 1983-1984
    - Editorial note for J.T.E., special issue
    - Addresses for J.T.E.
    - issue, 1982
    - Report on Detroit meetings, 1983
    - Memorandum
    - Discussion in Milwaukee, 1983
    - Written responses
  - Society of Professors of Education
    - DeGarmo lecture arrangements
    - DeGarmo lecture texts, Houston, February, 1982
    - Monographs, "Civic Learning in Teacher Education"
    - Civic Education, 1983
  - Teacher Education Network
  - American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education (A.A.C.T.E.)
    - AACTE Affairs, Detroit, 1983
    - Civic Education, 1982
    - Civic Education, Detroit, February, 1983
    - Foundation for Excellence in Teacher Education (Box 216)
  - American Educational Studies Association
    - Committee on Academic Standards and Accreditation
    - Nashville, 1982
    - Milwaukee, November, 1983
  - History of Education Society, October, 1976
  - Pacific Coast History of Education Society (P.C.H.E.S.)
  - American Educational Research Association
  - Society for the Study Curriculum History
  - Philosophy of Education Society (P.E.S.)
  - Social Science Education Consortium, Inc.
  - National Standing Conference on Humanistic and Behavioral Studies in Teacher Education, April, 1971 (Box 217)
  - American Educational Studies Association
    - Foundations Commission, Memphis, November, 1976
    - Foundations of Education Commission
  - Coordinating Council for Learned Societies in Education
  - Santa Clara County Council on Teacher Education, Teachers Center, 1976
  - California Commission for Teacher Preparation and Licensing, 1973-1974
  - Civic Based Teacher Education and Performance Based Teacher Education
- EXPERIMENTAL COLLEGE
  - Foundation, 1983-1984 (Box 218)
  - Alexander Meiklejohn Experimental College Foundation (A.M.E.C.F.), Business Meetings, August, 1983
  - A.M.E.C.F. stationary
  - General Program, I.L.S./A.M.E.C.F., Summer Institute, August, 1983
  - "Public and Private Values in Making Citizens," ILS/ Experimental College Institute, August, 1983
  - Northern California Group, (3 folders)
  - "Education for Intelligence," Meiklejohn's Wisconsin Experiment, 1927-1932
- LECTURE ARRANGEMENTS AND CONFERENCES
  - Society for the Study of Curriculum History (Box 219)
  - Memphis State University, Visiting Professor, 1980-1981
  - Memphis State University Lecture, February, 1974
  - College Entrance Examination Board (C.E.E.B.), 75th Anniversary Forum, Ocotber, 27, 1975
  - Education Commission of the States, Annual Meeting, Miami, June, 1974
  - I.D.E.A. Fellows Program, program and arrangements, July, 1974
  - N.E.A., Search for Freedom, March, 1959
  - C.E.E.B., Forum papers